<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-24T17:33:43-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sarah Martel</title><subtitle>TODO</subtitle><entry><title type="html">So You Bought A Domain. Now What?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/17/domain-name.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="So You Bought A Domain. Now What?" /><published>2024-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/17/domain-name</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/17/domain-name.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>It all started with a need.</em> I attend weekly tech meetups and often share event details on Discord with my group. But as the list grew, keeping things organized became a challenge. I realized that others—like friends outside the group—could benefit from these lists too. That’s when I decided to build a website. The moment my ideal domain name was available, I knew it was a sign to start. This blog will document how I got from <em>just a domain name</em> to a functioning website.</p>

<h2 id="-heres-what-well-cover">📝 Here’s What We’ll Cover</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Buying a Domain</li>
  <li>Hosting using GitHub Pages</li>
  <li>Adding Your Project</li>
  <li>Linking Your Domain to GitHub Pages</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="-buying-a-domain---lets-get-started">💲 Buying a Domain - Let’s Get Started</h2>

<p>I have another domain on Squarespace and it was easy to set up, so I decided to go with them again. There are plenty of places to host your domain and content, and you don’t need to use the same website for both.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/domain-search.png" alt="squarespace website domain search bar" />
<em>You’re not limited to .com; try something new like .pizza!</em></p>

<p>Note that the prices here are <em>ANNUAL</em> not monthly. Making a website can be affordable!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/domain-list.png" alt="squarespace list of your domains" />
<em>Here you can see my new website that’s about to be made and the one you’re currently on.</em></p>

<p>Now that you have a name, how do you get content on it?</p>

<h2 id="-hosting-on-github-pages-your-free-website-hosting-solution">👩‍💻 Hosting on GitHub Pages: Your Free Website Hosting Solution</h2>

<p>If you’re like me and want to keep things simple and affordable, GitHub Pages is a fantastic option. It’s free and perfect for hosting a straightforward website like this one.</p>

<h3 id="-step-1-create-a-new-repository-on-github">✅ Step 1: Create a New Repository on GitHub</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/new-repo.png" alt="New repository page GitHub" /></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Log in to your GitHub account (or create one if you don’t have it yet).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Click the “+” button in the top-right corner and select “New repository.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Give your repository a name—ideally, something relevant like my-awesome-site.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Make sure to:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Check “Public” so GitHub Pages can host it.</li>
      <li>Check “Add a README file” to make editing easier later.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>✨ <em>Pro tip: The repository name will be part of your GitHub Pages URL, so keep it concise!</em></p>

<h3 id="-step-2-enable-github-pages">✅ Step 2: Enable GitHub Pages</h3>
<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/settings.png" alt="GitHub settings" /></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Navigate to your repository’s Settings tab.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Scroll down to the Pages section.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Under Source, select the branch you want to use (typically main) and click Save.</p>
  </li>
  <li>GitHub will generate a URL for your site (e.g., https://yourusername.github.io/repo-name/).</li>
</ol>

<p><em>Your site will be live in seconds—magic!</em></p>

<h3 id="-step-3-add-your-website-files">✅ Step 3: Add Your Website Files</h3>

<p>Now that GitHub Pages is enabled, it’s time to add some content to your website. Don’t worry—no coding experience or fancy tools are needed for this part!</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Go to Your Repository on GitHub</p>

    <p>Navigate to the repository you just created.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/new-file.png" alt="Repo add new file" />
 <em>Click ‘Add File’ near the top right</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Add a New File</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Click the “Add file” button and select “Create new file.”</li>
      <li>Name the file index.html (this will be your website’s homepage).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Write Your Website Code</p>

    <p>In the text editor, paste this simple starter code:</p>

    <div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> <span class="cp">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;html&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;head&gt;</span>
     <span class="nt">&lt;title&gt;</span>Welcome to My Site<span class="nt">&lt;/title&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;/head&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;body&gt;</span>
     <span class="nt">&lt;h1&gt;</span>Hello, world!<span class="nt">&lt;/h1&gt;</span>
     <span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;</span>This is the beginning of my new website!<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;/body&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;/html&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/index.png" alt="Edit a new file screen" />
 <em>This is just to get started, we will change it soon.</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Commit Your Changes</p>

    <p>Scroll down to the bottom of the page. Under Commit new file, write a brief message like Add homepage and click the “Commit new file” button.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/commit.png" alt="Commit screen" />
 <em>Add a description if you like, but it’s not necessary</em></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="-step-4-check-your-live-website">✅ Step 4. Check Your Live Website</h3>

<p>Wait a few seconds, then visit the URL GitHub Pages provided earlier (e.g., https://yourusername.github.io/repo-name/). You should see your new website live!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/hello-world.png" alt="hello world site" /></p>

<h2 id="-linking-your-domain-to-github-pages">🔗 Linking Your Domain to GitHub Pages</h2>

<p>Now that your website is live on GitHub Pages, let’s connect it to your custom domain. Instead of a long GitHub URL, your visitors will type something sleek like yourcooldomain.com to see your site.</p>

<h3 id="-step-1-log-into-your-domain-registrars-account">✅ Step 1: Log Into Your Domain Registrar’s Account</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>This is the website where you purchased your domain (e.g., Squarespace, Namecheap, GoDaddy, etc.).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Navigate to the DNS settings or Domain management section for your domain.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="-step-2-add-or-update-dns-records">✅ Step 2: Add or Update DNS Records</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Delete any default DNS records, then add the following custom DNS settings to point to GitHub Pages.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/dns-settings.png" alt="DNS records" />
<em>Add in these five records. These are necessary to tell your domain registrar that your website content is being hosted on GitHub.</em></p>

<h3 id="-step-3-save-your-changes">✅ Step 3: Save your changes</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Save the DNS settings. Depending on your registrar, changes may take a few minutes to 48 hours to propagate.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="-step-4-find-your-github-pages-info">✅ Step 4: Find Your GitHub Pages Info</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Go to your GitHub repository.</li>
  <li>Navigate to Settings &gt; Pages, and under the “Custom domain” section, type your domain name (e.g., yourcooldomain.com) and save it.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>You might need to wait! Don’t worry if you initially get this error:</strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/improperly-configured.png" alt="Improperly configured error" /></p>

<p><strong>Or this error!</strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/improperly-configured-error.png" alt="Improperly configured error" /></p>

<p>Try again later today.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/dns-successful.png" alt="DNS successful" />
<em>I came back 6 hours later and now the DNS check was successful!</em></p>

<p>When everything is loaded and ready, you should also check the ‘Enforce HTTPS’ box for extra encryption protection. After waiting 6 hours, I was still unable to check the box. I will try again tomorrow.</p>

<p>✨ <em>Pro Tip: If your domain isn’t working after 48 hours, double-check:</em></p>

<ul>
  <li>The DNS records match GitHub’s recommendations.</li>
  <li>You typed the custom domain correctly in GitHub Pages settings.</li>
</ul>

<p>That’s it! If everything is set up correctly, you’ll see your GitHub Pages site live under your custom domain! Now it’s time to start coding and add some content. 😊</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="web-development" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It all started with a need. I attend weekly tech meetups and often share event details on Discord with my group. But as the list grew, keeping things organized became a challenge. I realized that others—like friends outside the group—could benefit from these lists too. That’s when I decided to build a website. The moment my ideal domain name was available, I knew it was a sign to start. This blog will document how I got from just a domain name to a functioning website.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Lean Startup: How Today’s Entrepreneurs Use Continuous Innovation to Create Radically Successful Businesses</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/10/book-review-lean-startup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Lean Startup: How Today’s Entrepreneurs Use Continuous Innovation to Create Radically Successful Businesses" /><published>2024-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-11-10T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/10/book-review-lean-startup</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/10/book-review-lean-startup.html"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/assets/images/books/the-lean-startup.jpg" alt="The Lean Startup book" width="200" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" />
  <div style="line-height: 1.4; margin-top: 5px;">
    <h4 style="margin: 5px 0; font-weight: normal;">Eric Ries</h4>
    <h4 style="margin: 5px 0; font-weight: normal;">2011</h4>
  </div>
</div>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p>This book introduces the Lean Startup methodology, a framework for building businesses that adapt quickly and innovate continuously. It combines lessons from successful startups with a systematic approach to validated learning and iterative development.</p>

<h2 id="why-i-read-this-book">Why I Read This Book</h2>
<p>I picked up this book to learn more about how startups use Lean methodology. While I was searching for books on Agile and Lean practices—not startups specifically—I thought it might still be relevant. I’m not ruling out starting a business someday, and despite its age, this book seemed like a valuable read. Plus, I was curious to learn from startup success stories.</p>

<h2 id="summary-of-key-ideas">Summary of Key Ideas</h2>
<p>Eric Ries shares insights from his experiences, particularly with IMVU, a now-dated instant messaging add-on. While I don’t remember IMVU myself, I found its story fascinating, especially how the company and others adapted their strategies through pivots and experiments.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h2>
<p>One story that stuck with me was about IMVU’s avatar movement feature. Instead of programming full character animations, the team built a minimal viable product (MVP) where avatars simply “teleported” across the screen. Surprisingly, users loved it and even considered it more advanced than games like The Sims. If the team had spent time perfecting full animations, the result might not have resonated with users—and it would have been wasted effort.</p>

<p>This resonates with me because it’s a reminder that my assumptions about what users want can be wrong. Until you put an MVP into users’ hands, you can’t truly know if you have a valuable product.</p>

<h2 id="application-to-practice">Application to Practice</h2>
<p>This book reinforced the importance of focusing on goals rather than jumping straight to features. As I work on projects with my team, I want to keep this in mind: new ideas are great, but it’s essential to stay aligned with the bigger picture and iterate based on real user feedback.</p>

<h2 id="strengths-and-weaknesses">Strengths and Weaknesses</h2>
<p>I appreciated the real-world examples of companies overcoming challenges and applying the Build-Measure-Learn loop, which aligns well with Agile principles. However, many of the companies mentioned, like IMVU and Grockit, are no longer relevant today. An updated edition would make the book feel more current and applicable.</p>

<h2 id="who-should-read-this-book">Who Should Read This Book</h2>
<p>If you’re thinking about starting a business or are curious about how startups operate, this book offers valuable lessons. It’s also a good read for anyone interested in the history of some notable companies and how they navigated challenges.</p>

<h2 id="favorite-quote">Favorite Quote</h2>
<p>“You can imagine our surprise when we started to get positive customer feedback. We never asked about the movement feature directly (we were too embarrassed). But when asked to name the top things about IMVU they liked best, customers consistently listed avatar “teleportation” among the top three (unbelievably, they often specifically described it as “more advanced than <em>The Sims</em>”).” – pages 108-109</p>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>
<p>I’d recommend this book if you’re curious about how companies learn to pivot and succeed. However, the examples feel a bit dated, so its relevance might depend on how much you want to learn from the past versus applying the ideas to today’s landscape.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-review" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Eric Ries 2011]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Sprint: How to Solve Big Problems and Test New Ideas in Just Five Days</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/06/book-review-sprint.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sprint: How to Solve Big Problems and Test New Ideas in Just Five Days" /><published>2024-11-06T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-11-06T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/06/book-review-sprint</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/06/book-review-sprint.html"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/assets/images/books/sprint.jpg" alt="Sprint book" width="200" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" />
  <div style="line-height: 1.4; margin-top: 5px;">
    <h4 style="margin: 5px 0; font-weight: normal;">Jake Knapp, John Zeratsky, Braden Kowitz</h4>
    <h4 style="margin: 5px 0; font-weight: normal;">2016</h4>
  </div>
</div>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p><em>Sprint</em> provides a framework for solving big problems and testing new ideas quickly through five-day “sprints” that encourage collaboration and creativity. The authors—experts from Google Ventures—explain how teams can prototype and test ideas with users in just one week.</p>

<h2 id="why-i-read-this-book">Why I Read This Book</h2>
<p>I’ve been thinking about how to lead a team during the software development process and how to incorporate the concept of sprints into our workflow. Typically, sprints last two weeks, but this book introduces a compressed version that can be done in just five full days. The idea was so unique that I had to read it to see how applicable it might be for my own projects.</p>

<h2 id="summary-of-key-ideas">Summary of Key Ideas</h2>
<p>The book outlines a five-day plan, broken down into clear activities aimed at creating and testing a prototype in a short amount of time. The process starts by defining a goal, sketching out ideas, building a prototype (which turns out to be simpler than expected), and testing with users. By the end of the week, teams can gain valuable insights into their product and the direction it should take.</p>

<p>One of the key takeaways is how much can be accomplished in just one week, using a streamlined process that forces focus and quick decision-making.</p>

<h2 id="what-i-learned">What I Learned</h2>
<p>I learned that the MVP (Minimum Viable Product) is often much simpler than expected. For instance, if you’re creating an app, the MVP doesn’t have to be a fully functional version; it could be something as simple as a slide presentation where users pretend to interact with the app. By observing how they navigate through the mockup, you can gather useful insights without building the actual product.</p>

<p>The book also includes inspiring stories, like the one about Time Timer, where the creator used overlapping paper plates to simulate the functionality of the timer. This showed me how even non-software projects can be prototyped and tested quickly. The book gave me several ideas for activities to try with my team, which helped us generate creative ideas and prototype designs more efficiently.</p>

<h2 id="application-to-practice">Application to Practice</h2>
<p>After reading the Monday and Tuesday chapters, I was eager to try something like this with my team. While we couldn’t dedicate five full days, we did have a 4-hour block of time. I called it a “Design Dash”—a mini sprint. I stocked up on Post-Its, whiteboard markers, and poster boards to document our progress. Snacks were highly recommended, and we made sure to have plenty!</p>

<p>For the sprint, we followed Monday’s plan closely, setting a concrete goal: “Motivate people, especially with ADHD, to achieve their goals through daily tasks.” We did a mapping exercise, though ours was a bit more complicated since we’re still figuring out how our app will function. For Tuesday, instead of the “Ask the Experts” activity, each of us presented on a concept we’d researched, sharing findings on MVP features. Though the research was already documented, hearing it aloud was much more impactful. We did this during the second part of our Design Dash, which lasted 3 hours (finding time as busy students is a challenge!).</p>

<p>We wrote “How Might We” questions, but we ran out of time to vote on the top ones. That will be the first item on the agenda for our next Design Dash.</p>

<h2 id="strengths-and-weaknesses">Strengths and Weaknesses</h2>
<p>The process is explained clearly, and the authors’ writing is engaging. One thing I wish was covered more in-depth is a “student version” of the sprint. While the book offers great resources for professionals, I had to improvise for my student team, and some student-specific advice would have been helpful.</p>

<h2 id="who-should-read-this-book">Who Should Read This Book</h2>
<p>This book is ideal for project managers, students (especially grad students like me who lead teams), and managers looking to improve their product or service. It’s a great read for anyone interested in fast-paced prototyping and problem-solving.</p>

<h2 id="favorite-quote">Favorite Quote</h2>
<p>One of the most inspiring parts of the book was about finding design inspiration outside the immediate domain of a product. For example, while designing a hotel delivery robot, the team realized that trying to create a talking, independently thinking robot would lead to unrealistic expectations. Instead, they focused on designing the robot’s “eyes” to communicate friendliness and personality. The team found inspiration in the peaceful, placid gaze of the animated creature Totoro from <em>My Neighbor Totoro</em>. A design by the company’s head designer combined this gentle aesthetic with a simple visual style, resulting in blinking eyes that perfectly suited the robot. As the authors described, “In Friday’s test, those simple blinking eyes conveyed a friendly personality, without promising conversation.”</p>

<p>Another example involved a coffee company designing an online store for selling beans. The team struggled to create an approachable way for customers to describe and choose flavors. Surprisingly, the breakthrough came from a chocolate bar wrapper, which featured a simple flavor wheel with descriptors like “bright” and “nutty.” Inspired by this minimalistic design, the team adapted the idea to create a flavor vocabulary for coffee beans. This cross-domain approach demonstrated how even unlikely sources can spark innovative ideas.</p>

<h2 id="closing-thoughts">Closing Thoughts</h2>
<p>I found this book so helpful that I decided to buy my own copy. After moving an entire bookshelf’s worth of books, I don’t usually buy books anymore and prefer to use my local library. But this book was worth the investment, as I want to keep the process handy for future reference and inspiration.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-review" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Jake Knapp, John Zeratsky, Braden Kowitz 2016]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Learning Agile - Understanding Scrum, XP, Lean, and Kanban</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/27/book-review-learning-agile.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Learning Agile - Understanding Scrum, XP, Lean, and Kanban" /><published>2024-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/27/book-review-learning-agile</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/27/book-review-learning-agile.html"><![CDATA[<div style="text-align: center;">
  <img src="/assets/images/books/learning-agile.jpg" alt="Learning Agile book" width="200" style="margin-bottom: 10px;" />
  <div style="line-height: 1.4; margin-top: 5px;">
    <h4 style="margin: 5px 0; font-weight: normal;">Andrew Stellman &amp; Jennifer Greene</h4>
    <h4 style="margin: 5px 0; font-weight: normal;">2014</h4>
  </div>
</div>

<h2 id="introduction">Introduction</h2>

<p><em>Learning Agile</em> gave me a feel for how the various agile methodologies would work in practice. In the past I’d only had a very basic understanding of Scrum and XP, and never even heard of Kanban. But now I have a better grip on these project management tools.</p>

<h2 id="general-thoughts">General thoughts</h2>
<p>The book did a good job explaining each methodology through examples. There is a narrative about a team working on a mobile app at a small company which is used to demonstrate the practices and how they can help.</p>

<p>Agile is about continuously improving, working with the customer early in the project. Get working software out there so the customer can give you feedback. Keep it simple so you can get the software done quickly, and keep repeating this cycle, making improvements to the product and process along the way.</p>

<p><strong>Scrum</strong> - Development time is broken down into 2 or 4 week sprints, with short daily scrum status meetings. The list of Project features that need to be built are stored in a backlog, and the Product Owner manages this. The team will decide what needs to be done next sprint and works together to make it happen. At the end of a sprint, the team holds a review meeting to demo the new software that is “<em>done</em> done”, and a retrospective to reflect on how well the sprint went. They can make changes to next month’s sprint if needed.</p>

<h2 id="how-it-relates-to-the-projecttakeaways">How it relates to the project/takeaways</h2>
<p>While we can’t go full-on Agile (that would make more sense if we weren’t students and were working full time on the project) I’ve found inspiration from the techniques presented in the book.</p>

<p>Daily scrum meetings are quick with each person answering these three questions:</p>

<ol>
  <li>What have I done since the last meeting?</li>
  <li>What will I do until the next meeting?</li>
  <li>What roadblocks are in my way?</li>
</ol>

<p>All of the teams working under my advisor meet on Monday and present the answers to these questions. Now I know where my advisor got it from!</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Getting that customer/user feedback early and often is key. It doesn’t matter if you or your boss likes the product. They aren’t the ones paying for it. That’s easier said than done, but using an agile methodology can help your team accomplish its goals and make great software.</p>

<p>Also I can’t help but wonder what it would be like to be a project manager/Scrum master. I might look into it.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-review" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Andrew Stellman &amp; Jennifer Greene 2014]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Bay Area Maker Faire 2024</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/20/bay-area-maker-faire-2024.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bay Area Maker Faire 2024" /><published>2024-10-20T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-20T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/20/bay-area-maker-faire-2024</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/20/bay-area-maker-faire-2024.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="what-is-this-maker-faire">What is this ‘Maker Faire?’</h1>

<p>I remember going to the Maker Faire pre-covid, and when I’d tell people that I’d have to try and explain what it was. It’s not a tech conference, its family-friendly, there’s vendors selling 3D printers, startups showcasing their product, and artisans selling jewelry and soap. But I think the slogan sums up up quite well:</p>

<h3 id="the-greatest-show-and-tell-on-earth">“The greatest show and tell on earth.”</h3>

<p>Basically, this event brought together people who make things, so that they may share their creations with those around them. It’s typically STEM related stuff, but it doesn’t have to be technical, electronics, that sort of thing. You can check out people’s projects on their blogs and social media, but seeing them up close is something special and inspiring. And that’s what I’m taking back home with me.</p>

<h2 id="a-source-of-inspiration">A source of <em>inspiration</em></h2>

<p>One of my favorite booths I stopped at was <strong>T &amp; A WORKSHOP</strong>, a group that makes cosplay props. Shawn Thorsson is the owner, whom I got to meet and chat about his amazing creations.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/tna.jpg" alt="tna" />
<em>Everyone at the booth was welcoming and happy to answer questions.</em></p>

<p>One thing that I’ll really remember is Shawn’s passion and excitement when he talked with me about his work. It was truly inspiring and makes me want to go home and make something.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/cosplay.jpg" alt="cosplay" />
<em>I saw this costume on display, and later, someone was walking around the audience wearing it!</em></p>

<p>The work here was impressive. It wasn’t just props, these were entire suits of fantasy armor and even this giant robot figure (sorry I don’t play video games and can’t tell you its name, but I’m a fan of it).</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/robot.jpg" alt="robot-thing" />
<em>This thing was huge. If it was hollow I’d be able to fit inside</em></p>

<p><strong>Do check out their website! https://tandaworkshop.com/</strong></p>

<p>I’m planning to go to Comic Con with some friends, and we’ve decided to dress as League of Legends characters. There are tons to choose from, and again, I don’t play the game but I think it would be a lot of fun to make and dress up for the con.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/Ashe_1.jpg" alt="ashe" />
<em>I picked this character because I liked the look of her dress and it was more sewing (which I am proficient in) than armor building</em></p>

<p>Reality is, I haven’t made <em>tooo</em> much progress with the costume…BUT seeing these impressive works of art is what I needed to essentially get started with this project.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/deepnest.png" alt="deepnest" />
<em>This is just a smal portion of the pieces. <a href="https://www.etsy.com/listing/1044469351/ashe-bow-wild-rift-pattern">I bought the pattern from Etsy here! - JJubsCosplay</a></em></p>

<p>There was a binder sitting on the table and I started flipping through the pictures and asked about how this prop was made. And I got to hear the whole story, how they 3D scanned an action figure, enlarged the pattern, and used that to draft the pieces. I didn’t even realize that was an option! They also had demonstrations on a vacuform machine which is used to make props. You can also make a mold, 3D print pieces; there are so many ways to solve this problem.</p>

<p>And that’s what programming is all about: solving problems. Maybe hearing the phrase “solve this problem” in relation to costume creation sounds funny, but the problem one has is, how do we make it? We become makers, creators, and build something amazing together.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/cosplay2.jpg" alt="cosplay2" />
<em>I don’t know what character is or what it’s from but it looks so cool!</em></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="fun" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What is this ‘Maker Faire?’]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mind Mapping Technique</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/mind-mapping-technique.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mind Mapping Technique" /><published>2024-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/mind-mapping-technique</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/mind-mapping-technique.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="getting-the-thoughts-out-there---using-lucidchart">Getting the thoughts out there - using Lucidchart</h1>

<p>Aside from this project, I’ve been on the lookout for an app where I can get my thoughts out and come back to them later. Maybe move them around and make connections. I have random thoughts often about little ideas for the project and just stuff in general. And what always happens is that it just stays in my head until some time later, when I’ll go,</p>

<h3 id="i-just-remembered-something-i-was-thinking-we-could">“I just remembered something! I was thinking we could…”</h3>

<p>Something like that. Well one of our group members suggested we make a mind map to organize our project’s ideas. Now this wasn’t in response to my search for a solution, but it inspired in me to try it on a personal level. Because the discussion we had and map we came up with was quite helpful.</p>

<h2 id="designing-a-map---a-collaborative-exercise">Designing a Map - A collaborative Exercise</h2>

<p>We couldn’t start making a mind map without knowing what it is we were trying to answer. As a follow-up to Tuesday’s meeting where we discussed what’s involved in a minimum viable product, I posed today’s question as:</p>

<h3 id="what-are-the-features-needed-for-an-mvp">What are the features needed for an MVP?</h3>

<p>While we are still working on our emphasize phase, there are features that are pretty certain will be in the app. And since this is just a design exercise, all ideas are encouraged. Here is the mind map we came up with.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/mind-map.png" alt="mind map" /></p>

<p>This was actually quite fun to make. The colors make it clear the 6 main functionalities we are considering. Of course, we could show the users a design with these implemented and find out what they want. If fact, <em>they</em> might not even know what they want!</p>

<p>The earlier we can start getting this tested, the better. Let’s do this!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meeting-notes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Getting the thoughts out there - using Lucidchart]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Minimum Viable Product</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/15/minimum-viable-product.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Minimum Viable Product" /><published>2024-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/15/minimum-viable-product</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/15/minimum-viable-product.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="whats-the-least-amount-of-and-most-important-features-we-need-to-make-for-the-design-so-that-we-can-start-testing">What’s the least amount of (and most important) features we need to make for the design so that we can start testing?</h1>

<p>As I read and learn more about software development and the various management techniques, the notion of a <strong>minimum viable product</strong> (MVP) comes up. I’ve come across this term before during undergrad courses, but now, we need to think seriously about it. One of the takeaways I’ve come from reading about Agile is about testing early and ofter.</p>

<h2 id="testing-is-important-for-so-many-reasons">Testing is important for so many reasons</h2>

<p><strong>Saving time -</strong> Imagine you came up with a cool app idea. It’s beautiful, does all you want it to do and functions smoothly. But the users say, “This is fine, but I wish you made it like <em>this</em>” and they present you with good ideas that will set you back. Changing the code functionality is a lot worse than fixing a bug. Let’s try to get this right the first time.</p>

<p><strong>Do they even want it? -</strong> This is the biggest concern I have for the project: figuring out what the user’s needs are, and developing a product to meet those needs. Not the other way around. You can’t just make a product and hope they will like it.</p>

<p><strong>It’s not just about the app! -</strong> Testing can and should begin as early as possible. I do need to get an IRB approval before testing with people, even for something as simple as an app. But you can ask your users about their opinions of wireframes drawn on paper. See how they “interact” and interpret the app’s functionality. I’d much rather change the wireframe than the code.</p>

<p>I’m excited to get this testing going and get some real user feedback!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meeting-notes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What’s the least amount of (and most important) features we need to make for the design so that we can start testing?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reaching Saturation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/reaching-saturation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reaching Saturation" /><published>2024-10-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/reaching-saturation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/reaching-saturation.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="how-do-you-know-when-to-stop">How do you know when to stop?</h1>
<p>We discussed the research that our group has been working on. Two students are looking through the App Store and Google Play Store for apps and gathering up their desriptions, pricing, app purpose, and reviews. We also have been creating a presentation of screenshots of the apps so we can easily compare their UIs. I’ve been looking at apps that specifically target ADHD (for task management and not symptamatology) and specifically use AI (AI is in the title or description). Another student was scraping Reddit posts to gather information about users with ADHD and write up a collection of user personas.</p>

<p>I was getting the feeling that some of the information was becoming repetitive. I said “I could keep looking at apps and reading more in the book (How to ADHD) but the same themes are coming up. Perhaps I could have stopped sooner, and have all the information I have now”. Just how many apps do you need to analyze before you feel like you have a comprehensive analysis of them?</p>

<h1 id="the-answer-is-not-all-of-them-because-this-isnt-a-systematic-review">The answer is “Not all of them!” because this isn’t a systematic review.</h1>

<p>The professor’s response was that we are “reaching saturation.” I didn’t consider it that way, but when she said that, I was immediately reminded of my Research Methods class. I expressed concern about having enough testers for the app. “Should I start asking now for volunteers to test the app next year?” The professor explained how you don’t actually need that many testers. You get diminishing returns at a certain point.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/new-information.webp" alt="Graph" />
<em>I asked ChatGPT to give me a picture of the graph I was thinking of so I can visualize this concept. This was the best I could get before I ran out of image creation calls.</em></p>

<p>It sounds like we are reaching saturation. On Tuesday we should synthesize this information so we can move forward. A student expressed that they would be willing to keep going on with the web scraping but was concerned if we should keep doing that. We don’t want to waste time doing something unnecessary!</p>

<p>I expressed that I like what we’ve got here and I’m looking forward to testing as soon as possible. I was sold on the whole testing early idea in lean and agile methodologies.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meeting-notes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How do you know when to stop? We discussed the research that our group has been working on. Two students are looking through the App Store and Google Play Store for apps and gathering up their desriptions, pricing, app purpose, and reviews. We also have been creating a presentation of screenshots of the apps so we can easily compare their UIs. I’ve been looking at apps that specifically target ADHD (for task management and not symptamatology) and specifically use AI (AI is in the title or description). Another student was scraping Reddit posts to gather information about users with ADHD and write up a collection of user personas.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ai Meetup</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/12/ai-meetup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ai Meetup" /><published>2024-10-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/12/ai-meetup</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/12/ai-meetup.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="aitech-coffee-social-">AI/Tech Coffee Social ☕</h1>

<ul>
  <li>Date: Saturday, October 12th, 2024</li>
  <li>Time: 10:00AM - 12:00 PM</li>
  <li>Location: Armistice Coffee Roosevelt</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-was-this-event-all-about">What was this event all about?</h2>
<p>This was a small gathering (about 20 people) for anyone working with or who has an interest in AI. It was hosted by Seattle AI Society. Everyone went around and introduced themselves and what projects they were working on.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/armistice_inside.jpg" alt="Inside coffee shop" />
<em>Inside the Armistice Coffee shop in Roosevelt</em></p>

<h2 id="my-thoughts">My thoughts</h2>
<p>I have been attending large meetups with 100+ people attending, so it was nice to go to something small for a change. It was exclusively a place to meet and talk with others who share a common interest. I enjoyed hearing other people’s stories and getting the chance to share my excitement about my project.</p>

<p>Everyone was friendly and there were a diverse backgrounds. From construction to health care, mental health and education, many fields were represented.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/seattle-ai-society.webp" alt="logo" />
<em>Consider attending an event!</em> <strong>https://www.meetup.com/ai-society/</strong></p>

<h2 id="would-i-go-again">Would I go again?</h2>
<p>Absolutely! I made some meaningful connections and hope to keep in touch. There were people that I wanted to talk to but there’s only so much time. Hopefully we will all be back next time.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meetups" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AI/Tech Coffee Social ☕]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Friday Meeting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/11/first-friday-meeting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Friday Meeting" /><published>2024-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/11/first-friday-meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/11/first-friday-meeting.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="friday-team-meeting-1---online-edition">Friday Team Meeting #1 - Online edition</h1>

<h2 id="yes-we-needed-to-meet-for-a-third-time-during-the-week">Yes, we Needed to Meet for a Third Time during the Week</h2>
<p>In the beginning I wanted to establish a Friday checkin. It would be a quick, kind of like what we do on the Monday meetings, where we state what we worked on, what we’re doing between now and the next week, and any roadblocks. But this would just be written on our Discord server. And it was nice to see everyone’s updates! I admit, it kept me on my toes because I didn’t want to say I did <em>nothing</em> or not enough. At the Tuesday meeting though, our professor mentioned “I think you guys will need to have another meeting besides today.” So I wanted to try doing Friday meetings instead of the checkin. We don’t have to meet in-person all the time, so its fine that this was online.</p>

<h2 id="what-we-talked-about">What we Talked About</h2>
<p>My plan was to do the following:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Understand the state of the project</li>
  <li>Each team member shares what they’ve been working on</li>
  <li>Brainstorm together our ~2 personas</li>
  <li>Any roadblocks and brainstorm ways to help/prevent</li>
</ol>

<p>I typed out a little blurb about where we were at with generating user personas, and why we’re doing this. This way everyone could be on the same page and ask questions. Next, my teammates and I talked about what we’d been working on.</p>

<p>I want to make a point in that we had been posting our research in our Discord server, but there’s something that’s more impactful when the author gets up (or in our case, unmutes) and presents their work. You get to hear everyone else’s ideas, and not your own assumptions. Discussions are sparked, instead of thoughts kept to oneself. Not to mention, its too easy for a link to get lost in a string of Discord posts, one that might have been posted but you were unable to read at that moment, and forgot about later.</p>

<p>I brought up about the drawing from the last Tuesday meeting and the categories for a user persona, so we discussed the user personas one of my teammates wrote up. It was interesting because there were overlaps with what I found. I did go through all the quotes from <em>How to ADHD</em> by Jessica McCabe and found some common themes. By the end of the meeting, we were able to pick out our 3 favorite personas, and will be presenting this on Monday’s meeting.</p>

<p>My other teammates are working on researching ADHD apps currently on the Play Store/App Store. Another question of ours is to see what features that users of these apps like and don’t like. It also came up to use the “Most helpful review” because they list the most helpful reviews, both positive and negative, at the top. Great way to help focus on what’s most important! We are also concerned with the design choices for these apps, so by Tuesday we’ll have a collection of app screenshots to visualize. We’ve already been looking through them, and some are quite beautiful and visually pleasing, while others maintain a minimalist design. I’m curious which style our users would prefer?</p>

<h2 id="this-weeks-takeaways">This Week’s Takeaways</h2>
<p>I probably didn’t need to go through every single quote bubble in <em>How to ADHD</em>. I did notice some common themes over time. While I didn’t <em>write down</em> every quote, I did flip through all the pages. The next step I want to work on is to go through the task management and ADHD apps with AI. But I don’t really need to go through all of them. My time would be best spent going through the most popular and established apps. Even if I only did 5.</p>

<h2 id="coming-up---goals-for-the-upcoming-days">COMING UP - Goals for the Upcoming Days</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Monday: Briefly present personas written up and app research</li>
  <li>Tuesday: More in depth discussion of what we found and start brainstorming solutions.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meeting-notes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Friday Team Meeting #1 - Online edition]]></summary></entry></feed>