<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.10.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2024-11-17T18:50:52-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Sarah Martel</title><subtitle>TODO</subtitle><entry><title type="html">So You Bought A Domain. Now What?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/17/domain-name.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="So You Bought A Domain. Now What?" /><published>2024-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2024-11-17T00:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/11/17/domain-name</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/11/17/domain-name.html"><![CDATA[<p><em>It all started with a need.</em> I attend weekly tech meetups and often share event details on Discord with my group. But as the list grew, keeping things organized became a challenge. I realized that others—like friends outside the group—could benefit from these lists too. That’s when I decided to build a website. The moment my ideal domain name was available, I knew it was a sign to start. This blog will document how I got from <em>just a domain name</em> to a functioning website.</p>

<h2 id="-heres-what-well-cover">📝 Here’s What We’ll Cover</h2>

<ol>
  <li>Buying a Domain</li>
  <li>Hosting using GitHub Pages</li>
  <li>Adding Your Project</li>
  <li>Linking Your Domain to GitHub Pages</li>
</ol>

<h2 id="-buying-a-domain---lets-get-started">💲 Buying a Domain - Let’s Get Started</h2>

<p>I have another domain on Squarespace and it was easy to set up, so I decided to go with them again. There are plenty of places to host your domain and content, and you don’t need to use the same website for both.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/domain-search.png" alt="squarespace website domain search bar" />
<em>You’re not limited to .com; try something new like .pizza!</em></p>

<p>Note that the prices here are <em>ANNUAL</em> not monthly. Making a website can be affordable!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/domain-list.png" alt="squarespace list of your domains" />
<em>Here you can see my new website that’s about to be made and the one you’re currently on.</em></p>

<p>Now that you have a name, how do you get content on it?</p>

<h2 id="-hosting-on-github-pages-your-free-website-hosting-solution">👩‍💻 Hosting on GitHub Pages: Your Free Website Hosting Solution</h2>

<p>If you’re like me and want to keep things simple and affordable, GitHub Pages is a fantastic option. It’s free and perfect for hosting a straightforward website like this one.</p>

<h3 id="-step-1-create-a-new-repository-on-github">✅ Step 1: Create a New Repository on GitHub</h3>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/new-repo.png" alt="New repository page GitHub" /></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Log in to your GitHub account (or create one if you don’t have it yet).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Click the “+” button in the top-right corner and select “New repository.”</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Give your repository a name—ideally, something relevant like my-awesome-site.</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Make sure to:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>Check “Public” so GitHub Pages can host it.</li>
      <li>Check “Add a README file” to make editing easier later.</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>✨ <em>Pro tip: The repository name will be part of your GitHub Pages URL, so keep it concise!</em></p>

<h3 id="-step-2-enable-github-pages">✅ Step 2: Enable GitHub Pages</h3>
<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/settings.png" alt="GitHub settings" /></p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Navigate to your repository’s Settings tab.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Scroll down to the Pages section.</li>
  <li>
    <p>Under Source, select the branch you want to use (typically main) and click Save.</p>
  </li>
  <li>GitHub will generate a URL for your site (e.g., https://yourusername.github.io/repo-name/).</li>
</ol>

<p><em>Your site will be live in seconds—magic!</em></p>

<h3 id="-step-3-add-your-website-files">✅ Step 3: Add Your Website Files</h3>

<p>Now that GitHub Pages is enabled, it’s time to add some content to your website. Don’t worry—no coding experience or fancy tools are needed for this part!</p>

<ol>
  <li>
    <p>Go to Your Repository on GitHub</p>

    <p>Navigate to the repository you just created.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/new-file.png" alt="Repo add new file" />
 <em>Click ‘Add File’ near the top right</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Add a New File</p>

    <ul>
      <li>Click the “Add file” button and select “Create new file.”</li>
      <li>Name the file index.html (this will be your website’s homepage).</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Write Your Website Code</p>

    <p>In the text editor, paste this simple starter code:</p>

    <div class="language-html highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> <span class="cp">&lt;!DOCTYPE html&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;html&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;head&gt;</span>
     <span class="nt">&lt;title&gt;</span>Welcome to My Site<span class="nt">&lt;/title&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;/head&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;body&gt;</span>
     <span class="nt">&lt;h1&gt;</span>Hello, world!<span class="nt">&lt;/h1&gt;</span>
     <span class="nt">&lt;p&gt;</span>This is the beginning of my new website!<span class="nt">&lt;/p&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;/body&gt;</span>
 <span class="nt">&lt;/html&gt;</span>
</code></pre></div>    </div>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/index.png" alt="Edit a new file screen" />
 <em>This is just to get started, we will change it soon.</em></p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Commit Your Changes</p>

    <p>Scroll down to the bottom of the page. Under Commit new file, write a brief message like Add homepage and click the “Commit new file” button.</p>

    <p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/commit.png" alt="Commit screen" />
 <em>Add a description if you like, but it’s not necessary</em></p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h3 id="-step-4-check-your-live-website">✅ Step 4. Check Your Live Website</h3>

<p>Wait a few seconds, then visit the URL GitHub Pages provided earlier (e.g., https://yourusername.github.io/repo-name/). You should see your new website live!</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/hello-world.png" alt="hello world site" /></p>

<h2 id="-linking-your-domain-to-github-pages">🔗 Linking Your Domain to GitHub Pages</h2>

<p>Now that your website is live on GitHub Pages, let’s connect it to your custom domain. Instead of a long GitHub URL, your visitors will type something sleek like yourcooldomain.com to see your site.</p>

<h3 id="-step-1-log-into-your-domain-registrars-account">✅ Step 1: Log Into Your Domain Registrar’s Account</h3>

<ul>
  <li>
    <p>This is the website where you purchased your domain (e.g., Squarespace, Namecheap, GoDaddy, etc.).</p>
  </li>
  <li>
    <p>Navigate to the DNS settings or Domain management section for your domain.</p>
  </li>
</ul>

<h3 id="-step-2-add-or-update-dns-records">✅ Step 2: Add or Update DNS Records</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Delete any default DNS records, then add the following custom DNS settings to point to GitHub Pages.</li>
</ul>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/dns-settings.png" alt="DNS records" />
<em>Add in these five records. These are necessary to tell your domain registrar that your website content is being hosted on GitHub.</em></p>

<h3 id="-step-3-save-your-changes">✅ Step 3: Save your changes</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Save the DNS settings. Depending on your registrar, changes may take a few minutes to 48 hours to propagate.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="-step-4-find-your-github-pages-info">✅ Step 4: Find Your GitHub Pages Info</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Go to your GitHub repository.</li>
  <li>Navigate to Settings &gt; Pages, and under the “Custom domain” section, type your domain name (e.g., yourcooldomain.com) and save it.</li>
</ul>

<p><strong>You might need to wait! Don’t worry if you initially get this error:</strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/improperly-configured.png" alt="Improperly configured error" /></p>

<p><strong>Or this error!</strong></p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/improperly-configured-error.png" alt="Improperly configured error" /></p>

<p>Try again later today.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/domain-name/dns-successful.png" alt="DNS successful" />
<em>I came back 6 hours later and now the DNS check was successful!</em></p>

<p>When everything is loaded and ready, you should also check the ‘Enforce HTTPS’ box for extra encryption protection. After waiting 6 hours, I was still unable to check the box. I will try again tomorrow.</p>

<p>✨ <em>Pro Tip: If your domain isn’t working after 48 hours, double-check:</em></p>

<ul>
  <li>The DNS records match GitHub’s recommendations.</li>
  <li>You typed the custom domain correctly in GitHub Pages settings.</li>
</ul>

<p>That’s it! If everything is set up correctly, you’ll see your GitHub Pages site live under your custom domain! Now it’s time to start coding and add some content. 😊</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="web-development" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It all started with a need. I attend weekly tech meetups and often share event details on Discord with my group. But as the list grew, keeping things organized became a challenge. I realized that others—like friends outside the group—could benefit from these lists too. That’s when I decided to build a website. The moment my ideal domain name was available, I knew it was a sign to start. This blog will document how I got from just a domain name to a functioning website.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/27/book-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book Review" /><published>2024-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-27T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/27/book-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/27/book-review.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="learning-agile---understanding-scrum-xp-lean-and-kanban">Learning Agile - Understanding Scrum, XP, Lean, and Kanban</h1>
<p>By Andrew Stellman &amp; Jennifer Greene</p>

<p>ISBN 978-1-449-33192-4</p>

<p><em>Learning Agile</em> gave me a feel for how the various agile methodologies would work in practice. In the past I’d only had a very basic understanding of Scrum and XP, and never even heard of Kanban. But now I have a better grip on these project management tools.</p>

<h2 id="general-thoughts">General thoughts</h2>
<p>The book did a good job explaining each methodology through examples. There is a narrative about a team working on a mobile app at a small company which is used to demonstrate the practices and how they can help.</p>

<p>Agile is about continuously improving, working with the customer early in the project. Get working software out there so the customer can give you feedback. Keep it simple so you can get the software done quickly, and keep repeating this cycle, making improvements to the product and process along the way.</p>

<p><strong>Scrum</strong> - Development time is broken down into 2 or 4 week sprints, with short daily scrum status meetings. The list of Project features that need to be built are stored in a backlog, and the Product Owner manages this. The team will decide what needs to be done next sprint and works together to make it happen. At the end of a sprint, the team holds a review meeting to demo the new software that is “<em>done</em> done”, and a retrospective to reflect on how well the sprint went. They can make changes to next month’s sprint if needed.</p>

<h2 id="how-it-relates-to-the-projecttakeaways">How it relates to the project/takeaways</h2>
<p>While we can’t go full-on Agile (that would make more sense if we weren’t students and were working full time on the project) I’ve found inspiration from the techniques presented in the book.</p>

<p>Daily scrum meetings are quick with each person answering these three questions:</p>

<ol>
  <li>What have I done since the last meeting?</li>
  <li>What will I do until the next meeting?</li>
  <li>What roadblocks are in my way?</li>
</ol>

<p>All of the teams working under my advisor meet on Monday and present the answers to these questions. Now I know where my advisor got it from!</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>Getting that customer/user feedback early and often is key. It doesn’t matter if you or your boss likes the product. They aren’t the ones paying for it. That’s easier said than done, but using an agile methodology can help your team accomplish its goals and make great software.</p>

<p>Also I can’t help but wonder what it would be like to be a project manager/Scrum master. I might look into it.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-review" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learning Agile - Understanding Scrum, XP, Lean, and Kanban By Andrew Stellman &amp; Jennifer Greene]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Mind Mapping Technique</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/mind-mapping-technique.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mind Mapping Technique" /><published>2024-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-18T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/mind-mapping-technique</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/18/mind-mapping-technique.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="getting-the-thoughts-out-there---using-lucidchart">Getting the thoughts out there - using Lucidchart</h1>

<p>Aside from this project, I’ve been on the lookout for an app where I can get my thoughts out and come back to them later. Maybe move them around and make connections. I have random thoughts often about little ideas for the project and just stuff in general. And what always happens is that it just stays in my head until some time later, when I’ll go,</p>

<h3 id="i-just-remembered-something-i-was-thinking-we-could">“I just remembered something! I was thinking we could…”</h3>

<p>Something like that. Well one of our group members suggested we make a mind map to organize our project’s ideas. Now this wasn’t in response to my search for a solution, but it inspired in me to try it on a personal level. Because the discussion we had and map we came up with was quite helpful.</p>

<h2 id="designing-a-map---a-collaborative-exercise">Designing a Map - A collaborative Exercise</h2>

<p>We couldn’t start making a mind map without knowing what it is we were trying to answer. As a follow-up to Tuesday’s meeting where we discussed what’s involved in a minimum viable product, I posed today’s question as:</p>

<h3 id="what-are-the-features-needed-for-an-mvp">What are the features needed for an MVP?</h3>

<p>While we are still working on our emphasize phase, there are features that are pretty certain will be in the app. And since this is just a design exercise, all ideas are encouraged. Here is the mind map we came up with.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/mind-map.png" alt="mind map" /></p>

<p>This was actually quite fun to make. The colors make it clear the 6 main functionalities we are considering. Of course, we could show the users a design with these implemented and find out what they want. If fact, <em>they</em> might not even know what they want!</p>

<p>The earlier we can start getting this tested, the better. Let’s do this!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meeting-notes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Getting the thoughts out there - using Lucidchart]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Minimum Viable Product</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/15/minimum-viable-product.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Minimum Viable Product" /><published>2024-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-15T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/15/minimum-viable-product</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/15/minimum-viable-product.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="whats-the-least-amount-of-and-most-important-features-we-need-to-make-for-the-design-so-that-we-can-start-testing">What’s the least amount of (and most important) features we need to make for the design so that we can start testing?</h1>

<p>As I read and learn more about software development and the various management techniques, the notion of a <strong>minimum viable product</strong> (MVP) comes up. I’ve come across this term before during undergrad courses, but now, we need to think seriously about it. One of the takeaways I’ve come from reading about Agile is about testing early and ofter.</p>

<h2 id="testing-is-important-for-so-many-reasons">Testing is important for so many reasons</h2>

<p><strong>Saving time -</strong> Imagine you came up with a cool app idea. It’s beautiful, does all you want it to do and functions smoothly. But the users say, “This is fine, but I wish you made it like <em>this</em>” and they present you with good ideas that will set you back. Changing the code functionality is a lot worse than fixing a bug. Let’s try to get this right the first time.</p>

<p><strong>Do they even want it? -</strong> This is the biggest concern I have for the project: figuring out what the user’s needs are, and developing a product to meet those needs. Not the other way around. You can’t just make a product and hope they will like it.</p>

<p><strong>It’s not just about the app! -</strong> Testing can and should begin as early as possible. I do need to get an IRB approval before testing with people, even for something as simple as an app. But you can ask your users about their opinions of wireframes drawn on paper. See how they “interact” and interpret the app’s functionality. I’d much rather change the wireframe than the code.</p>

<p>I’m excited to get this testing going and get some real user feedback!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meeting-notes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[What’s the least amount of (and most important) features we need to make for the design so that we can start testing?]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Reaching Saturation</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/reaching-saturation.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Reaching Saturation" /><published>2024-10-14T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-14T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/reaching-saturation</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/14/reaching-saturation.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="how-do-you-know-when-to-stop">How do you know when to stop?</h1>
<p>We discussed the research that our group has been working on. Two students are looking through the App Store and Google Play Store for apps and gathering up their desriptions, pricing, app purpose, and reviews. We also have been creating a presentation of screenshots of the apps so we can easily compare their UIs. I’ve been looking at apps that specifically target ADHD (for task management and not symptamatology) and specifically use AI (AI is in the title or description). Another student was scraping Reddit posts to gather information about users with ADHD and write up a collection of user personas.</p>

<p>I was getting the feeling that some of the information was becoming repetitive. I said “I could keep looking at apps and reading more in the book (How to ADHD) but the same themes are coming up. Perhaps I could have stopped sooner, and have all the information I have now”. Just how many apps do you need to analyze before you feel like you have a comprehensive analysis of them?</p>

<h1 id="the-answer-is-not-all-of-them-because-this-isnt-a-systematic-review">The answer is “Not all of them!” because this isn’t a systematic review.</h1>

<p>The professor’s response was that we are “reaching saturation.” I didn’t consider it that way, but when she said that, I was immediately reminded of my Research Methods class. I expressed concern about having enough testers for the app. “Should I start asking now for volunteers to test the app next year?” The professor explained how you don’t actually need that many testers. You get diminishing returns at a certain point.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/new-information.webp" alt="Graph" />
<em>I asked ChatGPT to give me a picture of the graph I was thinking of so I can visualize this concept. This was the best I could get before I ran out of image creation calls.</em></p>

<p>It sounds like we are reaching saturation. On Tuesday we should synthesize this information so we can move forward. A student expressed that they would be willing to keep going on with the web scraping but was concerned if we should keep doing that. We don’t want to waste time doing something unnecessary!</p>

<p>I expressed that I like what we’ve got here and I’m looking forward to testing as soon as possible. I was sold on the whole testing early idea in lean and agile methodologies.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meeting-notes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[How do you know when to stop? We discussed the research that our group has been working on. Two students are looking through the App Store and Google Play Store for apps and gathering up their desriptions, pricing, app purpose, and reviews. We also have been creating a presentation of screenshots of the apps so we can easily compare their UIs. I’ve been looking at apps that specifically target ADHD (for task management and not symptamatology) and specifically use AI (AI is in the title or description). Another student was scraping Reddit posts to gather information about users with ADHD and write up a collection of user personas.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Ai Meetup</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/12/ai-meetup.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ai Meetup" /><published>2024-10-12T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-12T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/12/ai-meetup</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/12/ai-meetup.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="aitech-coffee-social-">AI/Tech Coffee Social ☕</h1>

<ul>
  <li>Date: Saturday, October 12th, 2024</li>
  <li>Time: 10:00AM - 12:00 PM</li>
  <li>Location: Armistice Coffee Roosevelt</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="what-was-this-event-all-about">What was this event all about?</h2>
<p>This was a small gathering (about 20 people) for anyone working with or who has an interest in AI. It was hosted by Seattle AI Society. Everyone went around and introduced themselves and what projects they were working on.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/armistice_inside.jpg" alt="Inside coffee shop" />
<em>Inside the Armistice Coffee shop in Roosevelt</em></p>

<h2 id="my-thoughts">My thoughts</h2>
<p>I have been attending large meetups with 100+ people attending, so it was nice to go to something small for a change. It was exclusively a place to meet and talk with others who share a common interest. I enjoyed hearing other people’s stories and getting the chance to share my excitement about my project.</p>

<p>Everyone was friendly and there were a diverse backgrounds. From construction to health care, mental health and education, many fields were represented.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/seattle-ai-society.webp" alt="logo" />
<em>Consider attending an event!</em> <strong>https://www.meetup.com/ai-society/</strong></p>

<h2 id="would-i-go-again">Would I go again?</h2>
<p>Absolutely! I made some meaningful connections and hope to keep in touch. There were people that I wanted to talk to but there’s only so much time. Hopefully we will all be back next time.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meetups" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[AI/Tech Coffee Social ☕]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">First Friday Meeting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/11/first-friday-meeting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="First Friday Meeting" /><published>2024-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-11T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/11/first-friday-meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/11/first-friday-meeting.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="friday-team-meeting-1---online-edition">Friday Team Meeting #1 - Online edition</h1>

<h2 id="yes-we-needed-to-meet-for-a-third-time-during-the-week">Yes, we Needed to Meet for a Third Time during the Week</h2>
<p>In the beginning I wanted to establish a Friday checkin. It would be a quick, kind of like what we do on the Monday meetings, where we state what we worked on, what we’re doing between now and the next week, and any roadblocks. But this would just be written on our Discord server. And it was nice to see everyone’s updates! I admit, it kept me on my toes because I didn’t want to say I did <em>nothing</em> or not enough. At the Tuesday meeting though, our professor mentioned “I think you guys will need to have another meeting besides today.” So I wanted to try doing Friday meetings instead of the checkin. We don’t have to meet in-person all the time, so its fine that this was online.</p>

<h2 id="what-we-talked-about">What we Talked About</h2>
<p>My plan was to do the following:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Understand the state of the project</li>
  <li>Each team member shares what they’ve been working on</li>
  <li>Brainstorm together our ~2 personas</li>
  <li>Any roadblocks and brainstorm ways to help/prevent</li>
</ol>

<p>I typed out a little blurb about where we were at with generating user personas, and why we’re doing this. This way everyone could be on the same page and ask questions. Next, my teammates and I talked about what we’d been working on.</p>

<p>I want to make a point in that we had been posting our research in our Discord server, but there’s something that’s more impactful when the author gets up (or in our case, unmutes) and presents their work. You get to hear everyone else’s ideas, and not your own assumptions. Discussions are sparked, instead of thoughts kept to oneself. Not to mention, its too easy for a link to get lost in a string of Discord posts, one that might have been posted but you were unable to read at that moment, and forgot about later.</p>

<p>I brought up about the drawing from the last Tuesday meeting and the categories for a user persona, so we discussed the user personas one of my teammates wrote up. It was interesting because there were overlaps with what I found. I did go through all the quotes from <em>How to ADHD</em> by Jessica McCabe and found some common themes. By the end of the meeting, we were able to pick out our 3 favorite personas, and will be presenting this on Monday’s meeting.</p>

<p>My other teammates are working on researching ADHD apps currently on the Play Store/App Store. Another question of ours is to see what features that users of these apps like and don’t like. It also came up to use the “Most helpful review” because they list the most helpful reviews, both positive and negative, at the top. Great way to help focus on what’s most important! We are also concerned with the design choices for these apps, so by Tuesday we’ll have a collection of app screenshots to visualize. We’ve already been looking through them, and some are quite beautiful and visually pleasing, while others maintain a minimalist design. I’m curious which style our users would prefer?</p>

<h2 id="this-weeks-takeaways">This Week’s Takeaways</h2>
<p>I probably didn’t need to go through every single quote bubble in <em>How to ADHD</em>. I did notice some common themes over time. While I didn’t <em>write down</em> every quote, I did flip through all the pages. The next step I want to work on is to go through the task management and ADHD apps with AI. But I don’t really need to go through all of them. My time would be best spent going through the most popular and established apps. Even if I only did 5.</p>

<h2 id="coming-up---goals-for-the-upcoming-days">COMING UP - Goals for the Upcoming Days</h2>
<ul>
  <li>Monday: Briefly present personas written up and app research</li>
  <li>Tuesday: More in depth discussion of what we found and start brainstorming solutions.</li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meeting-notes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Friday Team Meeting #1 - Online edition]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Second Team Meeting</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/08/second-team-meeting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Second Team Meeting" /><published>2024-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-08T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/08/second-team-meeting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/08/second-team-meeting.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="tuesday-team-meeting-2-getting-the-hang-of-it">Tuesday Team Meeting #2: Getting the hang of it</h1>

<h2 id="ask-yourself-why-to-help-guide-you">Ask yourself “Why?” to help guide you</h2>
<p>I was truly looking forward to meeting with my team today. Its hard working away from everyone and trying to work together online, chatting in a Discord server. My teammates posted what they were working on, which was great! They went through the app store/play store to look up some ADHD/task management apps and get information like descriptions, number of downloads, reviews, and (my favorite) who made the app. Was it made by developers or were researchers involved?</p>

<p>But I feel like having a “Why?” would have helped. And an understanding.</p>

<p>My goal was to write user stories. I took software engineering; I’ve been reading about Agile methodology, of course we need user stories! It’s what you use to emphasize, figure out which features would help those hypothetical users, rather than just guessing what features your user needs. I knew what I needed. We thought about sources we could use to generate these user stories. In the past (undergrad) we just made them up. Because we didn’t understand why.</p>

<p>The goal shouldn’t have been “write user stores”. The goal should be “emphasize with our users, find out their needs, pain points, attributes, and write a story about your user”. This is WHY we need user stories. Not because I read about it in a book, but because it will help drive our project’s design and development.</p>

<p>Our professor helped guide our brainstorming with some helpful diagramming. I realized that we should only have a couple user stories. I was under the impression that I needed to systematically go through app reviews and Youtube comments to try and find who the users of this app could be, and make a huge list of their attributes.</p>

<p><img src="/assets/images/meeting2whiteboard.jpg" alt="Brainstoriming session during today's meeting" /></p>

<h2 id="mvp---minimum-viable-product">MVP - Minimum Viable Product</h2>
<p>This brings me back to the MVP. By only having a couple user stories, you are narrowing your scope, and thinking of quality vs quantity. <strong>It would be really unfortunate if we waste time making this app for so many different personas and they don’t even like it at all</strong>. The reason why we make user stories and personas is so that we have a focus and know exactly what we need, and make what’s necessary so we can start testing!</p>

<h2 id="answering-the-why-helps-figure-out-the-what">Answering the “Why?” helps figure out the “What?”</h2>
<p>Now that I know why I need to make these user stories, I am more informed about what I need to do. My plan during the next few days is to go through the book “How to ADHD” by Jessica McCabe (I’ve been reading it and it’s really good!). The book has quote bubbles with people speaking about their ADHD experience, and it just dawned on me today that those could be an excellent source of user story inspiration!.</p>

<p>Additionally, I want to go through the app store/play store and read reviews on apps that advertise using AI, since that’s what I want to do. I will look at the reviews, see what users like and dislike, and start gathering some info. And not to get in the systematic review mindset! That was for the systematic review PAPER, that’s not needed for this.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meeting-notes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Tuesday Team Meeting #2: Getting the hang of it]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Everyone Meeting2</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/07/everyone-meeting2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Everyone Meeting2" /><published>2024-10-07T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-07T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/07/everyone-meeting2</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/07/everyone-meeting2.html"><![CDATA[<h1 id="monday-meeting-2-reconvening-after-our-first-full-week-of-work">Monday Meeting #2: Reconvening after our First Full Week of Work</h1>

<h2 id="meetings-meetings-meetings">Meetings, Meetings, Meetings</h2>
<p>My individual team meets on Tuesdays, while we have an all-teams meeting on Mondays. I understand that some people don’t like meetings, or think that there are too many (waste of time). But there is merit to having two separate meetings. There is validity to all these meetings <em>as long as time is being spent wisely.</em></p>

<p><em>It is fun seeing the other team’s projects</em> - Some projects have been in development over several quarters, whereas mine is just beginning. It will be cool to see over the course of the next quarters what these projects evolv</p>

<p><em>Sometimes someone brings up a topic that applies to your project</em> - I talked a little about <a href="https://www.covidence.org/">Covidence</a>, a website that helps you process papers for a systematic review. It even creates a PRISMA chart for you that you can use for your paper! Another group is at a stage where they are sorting through sources and trying to keep track of the relevant ones. That, along with <a href="https://www.zotero.org/">Zotero</a> have been <strong>game changers</strong>. Zotero is great for personal projects and collaboration. You upload papers yourself <em>or with the plugin, directly from the website where you found the paper!</em></p>

<h2 id="takeaways">Takeaways</h2>

<p>Our Monday meetings consist of each student writing a 4x4x4 status report: 4 things you worked on, 4 things you will be working on for next week, 4 things that are blocking you (very Agile!). One of my challenges was communication. We all know how essential communication is, I even bring that up on day one when I teach, and how <em>good</em> communication is essential for many aspects in life. So working on this project is no different. I want to instill better communication between the team because we barely talked and I was wondering what was going on. A daily standup can be effective since you get that face-to-face time every day. Since that is not feasable here and we only have face-to-face once a week, I asked my group to give a small status update on every Friday. But that wasn’t enough. I think I need to initiate conversations more, asking specific questions on what they have tried, so we don’t wait unitl the weekly meeting to find out.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="meeting-notes" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Monday Meeting #2: Reconvening after our First Full Week of Work]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">4 Book Review</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/03/4-book-review.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="4 Book Review" /><published>2024-10-03T00:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2024-10-03T00:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2024/10/03/4-book-review</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2024/10/03/4-book-review.html"><![CDATA[<p>Mobile App Development for Businesses - Creating a Product Roadmap and Digitize Your Operations
Maja Dakic
9781484294758</p>

<p>** Did not finish **
I got up to page 168 (out of 376)</p>

<h2 id="general-thoughts">General thoughts</h2>
<p>This book seemed like it was more appropriate for businesses that already had an established product, and were looking to incorporate a mobile app as part of their product. Perhaps I should have focused in on the “for Businesses” instead of the “Mobile App” part of the title. It was published in 2023 so my expectations were higher since it wasn’t that old. Overall this book was broad without going into detail. For me, it was not helpful and talked about topics that didn’t relate, or that I already knew.</p>

<h2 id="how-it-relates-to-the-projecttakeaways">How it relates to the project/takeaways</h2>
<p>Chapters 3 (Create a Mobile App Product Roadmap) and 4 (Balance of Features in Mobile Development) did have some items that I took note of. The MoSCow method for feature prioritization is something I will use in the future. I’ve come across these sort of methods in other sources, so seeing it more than once from a different author reinforces its importance and reminds me of how I can use it.</p>

<p>The book listed some roadmap template tools, which were only free for a trial period. Of course there are others out there and I’m not sure if we need something like that. But just making a note in case it’s something I need at some point. They also mentioned software for wireframes: Axure, Moqups, and Mockplus (pg. 143).</p>

<p>I did like this bubble sort priorizitation from chapter 4, basically keep comparing two features and see which is most important until you have a list in order with the most important features at the top.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">Conclusion</h2>
<p>I completely lost interest at the part that talked about brainstorming features but didn’t include actually testing with your users. Just “think in the users shoes” and that the QA team will take care of it. I should have stopped earlier and not wasted time that could have been spent reading a more helpful book. Ignore the feeling of needing to be a completionist like reading is some sort of game achievement!</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="book-review" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Mobile App Development for Businesses - Creating a Product Roadmap and Digitize Your Operations Maja Dakic 9781484294758]]></summary></entry></feed>